it seemed like there's something about
the way that the human mind can be made
unable to relate to the world and
instead run a program run an ideology
where it constantly refrains its
perceptions in accordance with the
ideology as opposed to honestly in
humility relating to reality the Nate's
exquisitely vulnerable to control I
would maybe bring in the ensigns idea of
the bewitchment of language the idea I
think he said philosophy is about I not
know the exact quote but it is
effectively undoing the process of the
bewitchment of language that there's
something in the nature of language the
nature of being able to think in
concepts that somehow flips into making
us a prisoner of those concepts well
interestingly enough very cool so as you
were speaking you actually said I wish I
had the quote and that's the Richmond of
language which is to think that the
exact specification of the actual sounds
is the thing but it's not it's the
essence of what he was trying to say and
so to convey the essence is the thing
that we actually want yes you did which
is why I was so interesting like it
popped in I actually initially was
struggling with the actual words and
then I realized what I really just need
to do is to listen it was trying to
express itself through the words I think
this is very I think that's like a big
idea that's not like a magic imagine
that I'm not very good at expressing
myself and also imagine them trying to
express something which is both deep and
important well either you're going to
eat just gonna have to ignore me right
and just move on because I'm not going
to be able to give it to you whole cloth
in sort of perfectly wrapped magical
material or we're gonna have to
work together we're gonna have to both
identify and recognize there's something
here then maybe I have some piece of and
if you can sense it at all that means
you have a piece of it too so now we're
never and collectively to kind of get a
size of this thing you know it's the
blind the blind men and the elephant
except in this case maybe you're seeing
it and I'm hearing it and I can kind of
describe it as this sound is I don't
really know what it is like yeah this
was maybe it's coming from this kind of
large lumpy object
that's neat well everything interesting
is gonna be of that sort - never been
said before then it's very unlikely that
I have a very clean way of expressing it
and if it's interesting it's likely it's
going to be hard to express and so we
enter into that and we enter into a
place where if you see if you perceive
the words that I'm using as being more
of a map more of a hint more of a way to
try to sort of begin the process of
orientation around something which is
itself transcendent and we're
endeavoring to actually find a way to
tune in to the transcendent using the
words literally just as a way to make it
more real more shareable more clear what
does it look like do you think that what
we need to do to come together or to -
to be able to form the collective
intelligence that's going to get us
through the next five 10 15 years well I
actually think it's mmm relatively as
they said that's easily done
it seemed like there's two basic moves
the first move where we've used the
phrase exit or escape the matrix so it's
something along the lines of free your
mind and your body from this legacy
environment this legacy civilization the
blue church and all the other coach mo
of that environment most notably your
mind the second move is well making more
complex of news become sovereign find
the others in turn to a you know two or
more among us in my name with them enter
into collaboration with them become
sovereign as a group in some sense
that's it because that thing that
gathering of sovereigns who are entering
into a relationship of higher level
sovereignty has a level of consciousness
and a level of intelligence and love of
wisdom that is well certainly much more
than any of us as individuals or any
existing institution has now the only
real novelty that the only thing that we
don't
actually know how to do it all is how to
do that with more than an old-fashioned
tribe of people so we can build the
skill its ambient it's part of our basic
toolkit being people if we can we can
unlearn a lot of the adaptive techniques
and strategies and habits and biases of
civilization one of what I call game a
the blue church and all of its past
versions I've done learn that a lot of
it we learn a lot of these basic thing
but the basic things are still basic so
we can relearn that we can instantiate
the basic human toolkit of how to be
people with each other and in that
environment we have what it takes to be
able to enter into this relationship of
coherence but evolution only got us up
to be 150 people it's called the Dunbar
limit one of intellectuals sort of the
the maximum size of a fully coherent
tribe we should be mindful of the fact
that that makes that that's actually
truly coherent only in the context where
we're all related really a tribe like
every single person that I was born in
that tribe and raised in that tribe then
you have a co here could be 150 these
days with practice maybe can get up to
30 or 50 I'm sure there's some
communities can get a little bit higher
but not a lot but our challenge is
actually harder just doing that as great
as that would be doesn't actually solve
the problem we actually did figure out
how to deal with everybody we have to
find a way to scale coherence well
beyond a hundred fifty maybe even all
the way to everybody certainly into the
small - 2015 150,000 that's new right
but the way we're going to get there is
about this first step yeah so
individuals becoming sovereign
recovering that which is theirs
in the first place and then entering
into this relationship of coherence with
other individuals and becomes skillful
at that becoming masterful with that and
then using that from that place then
doing the next work that's the place to
do the next work what I find most
problematic painful and distressing is
when people try to do it from the old
place it won't work it can't work that
style of thinking and the style of
coordination of working together it's
just a moment with a job there's sort of
what's coming through for me is I sort
of sense of trusting the field and it's
very difficult to express this in a way
that doesn't feel
sort of not crunchy enough for kind of
game a type people but the sense is if
we are able to come together in in that
space then the right answers by
definition will come up because that's
the nature of creativity that's the
nature of consciousness that's the
nature of getting out of our own way
enough for the right things to arise
well I I don't feel that I have to go
bet sounded to me like it was teeny
illogical hmm and then maybe I think the
point years I don't know I don't think
anybody knows I think something kind of
thing you can't know but I'm hurt I need
you because the only thing that you can
really endeavour to do is the best that
you can do and maybe that it's not
enough it may be that we do not have it
in us to make it through this but this
is the way that we can do the best that
we can do and so if it is there if the
answer is to be found this is the way to
find it and to feel that it is a
meaningful endeavor to do so so that
even if the answer isn't there our
effort was meaningful how does this link
to sovereignty so we're dealing with it
word a sound and I want to act to put
that in your mind first we deal with a
sound sovereignty which by the way if
your mind is the kind of mind that knows
how to speak language is going to
interpret that as a word and then if it
uses words and associates then with best
with meaning it's gonna download a whole
scheme of meaning note if it doesn't
have to you could just choose to listen
to it as this sound there is what I'm
saying that is that it's very important
in the context of sovereignty to be able
to actually take responsibility for all
of these steps because in a conversation
with somebody they may utter a sound
that you goddamn think means something
specific and they need something
completely different
and if you can't actually be able to
slow down and say hold on wait a minute
I thought you said this as opposed to
getting into an argument but what you
for sure no they said be Emma - you slow
down and say I wait there's something
something's off not quite sure where it
is it's back up a bit
oh when you use the word the sound you
added to sound sovereignty it seems like
you may have something different than
what John Locke was writing about or
with the the folks in Montana keep
carrying on about what do you mean by
that let me describe what I mean by it
and the reason why I'm doing this is
because I think a what I'm describing is
a more powerful version of the essence
of what that term has long intended to
mean I'm kind of recovering it from the
legacy of feudalism wrenching it finally
from those from the grips of London
and finally putting it back in the place
where it belongs which is in fact
sovereign individuals but then they were
to do that I have to actually give it
the meaning right you aren't born
sovereign that's reapplying the
feudalist model right you're born in the
king to this new thing what does it mean
to be sovereign well it means to be
sovereign is well for two months
contextual it describes the degree to
which you have the capacity you have the
ability to respond to the circumstances
that you find yourself in in such a way
as to maintain or increase your ability
to respond to the circumstances in which
you find yourself in it's very simple
it's a loop right so let's say for
example I am sober and I am standing and
I am sovereign in the context of
standing I mean that I can keep dandy
there like Adele spontaneously fall down
as relatively low keep drinking at a
certain point I actually lose my
sovereignty I will spontaneously
transform when instead of standing there
state of no longer standing I've
destroyed my sovereignty in the domain
of standing we can do this all over the
place oftentimes say fighting or martial
arts is a good one
so every martial artists including
boxing and fencing think that is aware
of the fact that there's a relationship
between your balance your Center where
you are in terms of poised in ability to
act and then what happens when you
extend yourself and so in an optimal
space I'm in this place where I can I
can respond to anything you do as
swiftly as I can with maximum impact and
with a maqam ability to be able to
respond to the next moment right so I
don't want to get into a place where I'm
something on my heels where my balance
is off I don't want to swing so hard
that if I miss I'm not completely
vulnerable I can't do anything if I do
swing very hard I mean that calculated
choice the next thing I have to do have
to get back into into balance that to
get right into the stance just like a
physical example the answers have the
same sensibility rights it's a sense of
being able to be centered and poised but
it's always in relationship to a context
and it's always very complex you let's
say do you ever watch the the French
soccer players Enedina Zidane we might
say that he was very sovereign in the
domain of soccer but not particular
sovereign the domain of having his
sister critiqued by an Italian soccer
player if you recall right he went from
being a masterful champion of soccer to
somebody who's head-butting somebody in
a field in getting his ass kicked off
the field right so his sovereignty was
masterful in one domain but had a sort
of fractal or a very specific
vulnerability that got popped and caused
the whole it cause the whole thing to
pop right he literally got removed from
the field is no longer even a soccer
player
so this is the idea now what we can do
is we can generalize that so I can speak
about your sovereignty in a given domain
and then I can sort of think about your
general sovereignty which is your
sovereignty and an arbitrarily large
number of domains and of course that
involves more general capacities so and
that's that's like the get a man of fish
eats for a day teach them in a fish eats
forever you could become sovereign in
some domain but you can also build a
higher order capacity which gives you a
generalized capacity for sovereignty in
all domains so for example the capacity
of discernment or the capacity of just
self-awareness so she could do a simple
in knowing what your emotional state is
being able to be conscious of your
emotional state is a general purpose
always useful ingredient of any form of
sovereignty and if you know that your
opponent is goading you and it's making
you angry and that's taking you out of
your game well that at least gives you
the ability to maybe choose not to be so
angry now if you have your game if you
know that you're getting anxious and
fearful while you're trying to walk
across the tightrope and that's gonna
cause you to fall then okay maybe again
so that that's a more fundamental
capacity within general purpose
sovereignty there's a whole list of
these kinds of capacities so let me hold
that for a second come back so now have
a basic idea what sovereignty means in
this context the way that I'm trying to
use it now what I want to say is the
reason when that concept is so powerful
an important is the sovereignty is what
is necessary to be able to play a role
in this new emergent sense-making
fabric I remember in the broadcast model
you had to be sort of a very high
quality computer in this new model you
have to be sovereign and the more
sovereign you are the more effectively
you can actually play a role in this
thing because the more capacity you have
to receive from the world to process it
in a way that is responsible you can
actually respond to it with the fullest
aspect of what is you have to bear to it
you're not merely what's knocking out of
that once and you have the ability to
choose the best choice that you can make
whatever it happens to be it may be that
you're not ready you haven't got any
choices but you can must choose the best
choice and you can send that best choice
out with the highest degree of
skillfulness and you can bring out so
now you've got a an ability to listen an
ability to discern and sense and then
your ability to express if you have
these three aspects in high symmetric
relationship and in a sovereign
containers that they're able to be
Integris against various forms of
challenge which can be all kinds of
things like one one thing that might
overwhelm your sovereignty is just the
velocity of input if you hook yourself
up to social media just like scroll
through Facebook for ten hours
you're probably overwhelming your
sovereignty most people's brains can't
handle that much dopamine and serotonin
and you know nonsense other words are
actually more simple if you haven't been
eating at all for the past 10 hours
you're likely breaking your sovereignty
now your body needs fuel to operate to
be able to operate effectively so
religion and to some extent also
spirituality building practices that are
able to support an increase in
individual sovereignty so as to be able
to enter into relationships with others
so as to increase your collaborative
sovereignty these are properly spiritual
and religious domains so now we're
actually reinvigorating the whole notion
of religion we're using a more
fundamental definition I guess this is
the big paradox for me about meaningful
collaboration can only happen from a
point of deep individual sovereignty to
really connect and really connect with
someone else can only come from a place
of being fully resourced in myself well
you weren't used were deep so as long as
you use the word deep I completely agree
and we can have we can have meaningful
collaboration even we're both in
recently poor sovereignty it's just we
just got lucky or it hit us in a place
that was most needful and it may be that
the thing that our collaboration did is
gave rise to how to increase our
sovereignty but for sure if we want to
use collaboration reliably and we want
to go really deep this is now
conditioned on a depth of sovereignty
and a depth of skillfulness in listening
having discernment and then expressing
clearly right so the capacity to be
present to what's happening without
allowing yourself to be moved out of
your skillfulness and then the actual
skillfulness to be able to deal with
that situation well or what is what
needs to happen and again we can talk
about this in particular domains like
maybe in say computer science as a
programmer but there's in this new world
things aren't simple you aren't a
computer programmer you may be playing
the role of computer programmer for 15
minutes but then you're also doing all
kinds of things constantly it's
constantly flowing and read jiggering
and maybe actually had a very
interesting person writing a message
yesterday about decentralized autonomous
organizations noticing that an evil to
be able to deal with these things that
designed them you had to sort of somehow
be a sociologist an anthropologist an
economist and a computer scientist
simultaneously it's like yes a real good
example and by the way that will be a
spontaneous emergence of a particular
cluster of capacities that might be the
thing that you do for the next three or
four hours and then you're going to
shift and now you're going to be a
relation
in a relationship with another person
and we're making food right and of
course we know that we do that now but
we do that now in these weird kind of
like disciplinary blocks in the future
these things and I even in the future in
the present these things are flowing and
they're mutating very very rapid we're
just in a world of faster change and
more fluidity so in this world of
fashion changing more fluidity your
sovereignty and your skillfulness need
to be based on the most invariant things
so you can't just have say skillfulness
computer programming which is like give
a man a fish you need to have
skillfulness in learning or even having
skillfulness on the basis that how one
becomes having a high capacity of being
able to learn that's the deep basis if
you build a a deep basis of sovereignty
and a deep basis of mastery
then you're fully prepared to
participate in any form of collaboration
in any context and now things get very
powerful because let's say you find
yourself with a group of 10 people
you've never met before in a space you
don't understand seems odd now but in
the future we're gonna see that a lot
well what do you do well all you do is
you each is individual figure out how to
get fully clear on your own sovereignty
and whatever things you do to be able to
really okay calling this up I need to be
fully sovereign thank you you know
martial arts you get in a fighting
stance and then you start from nothing
with each other you know for sure that
you don't yet know anything to begin to
play experimental II you try different
things and if you're all skillful if you
all are aware of how this works and
you're all sovereign so I say something
to you that to a blue church snowflake
would trigger them out of their mind
but your sovereign so you're aware the
fact that we're right now in a space of
experimentation and playfulness which
doesn't mean necessarily that you are
allowing me to abuse you what it means
is that you're listening and you're able
to discern and you're able to be aware
wait a minute he's actually abusing me
clearly you actually are able to have
perception on that and you can even
respond to that say hey wait a minute I
think we just moved into a weird space
what's going on here and you can
actually address it effectively clearly
call it out in a way that allows me to
realize whoa you're right I was actually
out of my sovereignty there and bring it
back in and that of course is crucial
I'm gonna call this coherence so
coherence is when people are able to
enter into a relationship where they
basically been to form an emergent whole
as emergent properties that is greater
than the individuals involved greater
than the sum of the parts
and to achieve coherence first and
foremost requires both sovereignty and
awareness of sovereignty when you have
it and you're aware where you are and a
continual consciousness of recognizing
that
you have to maintain a certain level of
sovereignty to be able to enter into
coherence at all and the be incoherence
has the highest intelligence the highest
capacity to perceive and respond to the
whatever is going on
so you prioritize that so first - opera
- yes okay cool
now are we in coherence yes okay cool
now and start trying to do something if
not if something's out of coherence okay
how do we get back in coherence oh is it
because I'm out of sovereignty Oh get me
to get back into sovereignty and kind of
building back up one of the practices or
techniques to build sovereignty the me
do it in terms of sort of dimensions
because we can simplify a bunch of
pieces there's the body and the body is
the basis of sovereignty so it's kind of
simple like imagine a two-year-old who
is cranky is not sovereign you can
actually think of your body as your
little two-year-old so you have to learn
to take care of yourself how to parent
yourself at level the body so learn how
to make good food choices learn when
you're dehydrated it's amazing how often
people are dehydrated and how confuse
they are by the fact that they are in
fact unable to think clearly and have
clean emotions when they're dehydrated
it's not confusing your body it's a core
metabolic necessity tired are you tired
right always very basic things like a
scent it's silly but almost everybody
gets it wrong almost all the time so
learn how to parent yourself with the
level of the body for most people alive
today the next one's going to be be
aware of your trauma I mean the reality
is that they were all effectively
enormous walking bags and crazy trauma
and all the various defense mechanisms
that have built up around those traumas
and everything experience we have is
filtered through that well unfortunately
that's just the case hopefully in a
future civilization were able to create
human beings who don't have that in
which case that won't be a major issue
but here it is so to the degree to which
you can just work through that trauma it
generally sucks it's very painful and
scary and can lead to having action make
changes in your life which are
themselves painful and scary but
nonetheless the more you can work
through that the better if you if you
find that you're going to be engaging in
a race it's probably useful to have
learned how to walk first same thing
here if you're going to be interacting
with other people the more you could
have done the work beforehand that has
either eliminated or addressed the
trauma and the defense mechanisms or at
least has made them conscious
and then of course also build practices
and techniques and how to respond and
bring yourself back into sovereignty
when you find these various defense
mechanisms and traumas are hijacking you
there's a good concept called amygdala
hijack this is actually a lot of very
straightforward neurology but if you
feel like you're under threat the say
for example if somebody shows up who
happens to evoke the feeling of a bully
who used to beat you up and you don't
even even conscious of that is some of
your body is under threat you may
actually literally experience a big deal
hijack meaning that the blood is being
pulled from the prefrontal cortex and
being put into your Lindex system for
fight-or-flight responses well the neck
is you're not sovereign but one of
things you can do and then this gets two
things one is you may have some habits
we've worked on practices that you've
trained yourself to do when you're out
of sovereignty this is like a martial
artist who's trained how to get back up
when they've been knocked down like
you've worked that over and over again
until it's just unconscious so you work
there again and the second course is
then also to always flag yay I just got
knocked out of sovereignty awesome I've
just been able to identify a blind spot
that I wasn't aware of before learn how
to be attracted to that
rather than avoid it actually see how
well you can train yourself to be
attracted to experiences that traumatize
you not to get into trauma not to be
traumatized but to get into experiences
that are triggering because of past
trauma so that you can become conscious
of it so they can see it and learn what
the shape of it is and then you can of
course going to address it and then
ameliorate so you can come back in the
next level is psychological and
cognitive so at the psychological level
if you are still running if you're still
computer but if you're still running the
simulator of thinking rather than
thinking itself one be aware of that
notice the difference between them and
begin the process of trying to figure
how to rebuild for yourself your
capacity to think now the good news is
that's ambient right that's how were
born
fortunately human beings are broadly
speaking born with a natural seeking and
exploring creative thinking capacity it
is beaten out of us it is not natural
and so to the degree to which to begin
relearning that and we can double click
on that if you'd like then you're moving
into a space of being able to think and
this includes things like not thinking
you know the answer nothing can you
understand somebody not using the
process of inter of communication to
achieve power or dominance over someone
else this office oftentimes with Shep is
for example willful misinterpretation or
self-righteousness and these are also
characteristics of what not
thinking looks and feels like thinking
looks and feels like curiosity it feels
like well humility it feels like slowing
down it feels like having a habit of
responding to confusion by slowing down
and be more careful as opposed to
speeding up and skipping over it at the
cognitive level now we've got this
notion of transparent comedic mind
there's really neat concept called
mapping mapping has to do with the fact
that everybody learned everything by
virtue of actually experiencing things
and then connecting some portion that
experience with some notion like dog dog
has a map you have an experiential
manifold of all the various dogs who's
experienced particular ones when you
first experienced dogs and the notion
the word dog kept being associated with
something in that experience are
manifold it first who knows he may have
cut out some big chunk of experience
associated with dog with like furry
fuzzy thing that's drooling on me and
also the couch cuz you're a baby you
havin fun idea
but over time is sort of the
differentials sort out you've got a
fuzzy thing which is dog well the point
here that you're mapping is gonna be
mapping to some stuff that actually
isn't part of that just for you much
less for other people and so I say
sovereignty you've got a mapping well
we've just gone through the process at a
cognitive level we can recognize that
mapping errors are just mapping errors
so flag got a mapping here it what you
just said is make sense to me is this
because I'm mapping it wrong or is it
because I'm not understanding what you
just said okay cool
anybody that's also a practice but the
concept is useful yeah I mean there's
lots more but these are examples yes
good I've been talking about that in
terms of the context of mysticism so
let's go into the notion of self
integration this is a key one this is
actually the combination so I did body
and I did psychology I didn't do the two
so let's bring the two together
meditation is the the becoming
exquisitely aware of awareness of how it
is the you show up as self absent all of
the things and its relationship with
mind all right so one of the aspects of
meditation is learning how to separate
mind from self learning how to separate
or really it's actually the computer
mind the programmatic mind from that
thing objection is the origin of deeper
thinking so it's both useful in the
sense that it helps you actually
separate those two and necessary in the
sense that it's a primary practice of
being able to come into clarity of self
which is the basis of all these other
things and to do learn things like
acceptance like how to actually be
available to an open to what reality is
actually conveying as opposed to
endeavoring to cause it to be what you
want it to be it's a practice it is for
that it does that as that's the you can
only get that through that practice
that's one of the things that practice
is doing and then another one is this
notion of integration this notion of
being able to become very aware of all
the different aspects of mind and self
and body and how they're showing up on
what they're trying to say and being
able to become compassionate I suppose
we're loving so as to allow them to
express themselves not to repress to
herself not to be a tyrant to yourself
not to have some aspect of yourself
calling out and trying to call something
up and to show it's up and speak itself
and repress it and shut it down because
then if you do that you're disintegrate
you're out of integrity and this will
create well it'll create havoc actually
it'll force to work come to bite you in
the ass at some point and make you
extremely vulnerable to a wide variety
of blind spots in sovereignty space so
and of course the key to that is self
acceptance so member I talked about the
mission of acceptance well the recursion
on that it's actually able to enter into
acceptance with self so you can actually
allow the parts of you that you may
judge you may want to have your sort of
computer mind has been somehow trying to
say isn't a good thing or should not be
happening and actually to allow those
things to show up and to I'm gonna say
honor that more than accept them because
what you're doing is you're actually
allowing them to be revealed as the
purity of the essence of what they are
which they are right but they may not be
able to be clearly that until you've
actually honored them is there's a lot
of depth here this is not trivial stuff
at all
and I'm not even doing it particularly
well but that's some of it as both and
returning to the kind of the matrix idea
what we are we're talking about I see
that that metaphor as being about
individuation ultimately it's all about
individuation it's like how do you it
scag the traps of ideology how do you
escape the traps of your thought running
down conceptual lines because that's
what we used to and becoming truly
ourselves which is what you were talking
about the sovereignty and that that for
me is is kind of the framework of the
matrix I guess if if what we're talking
about is escaping from that it is the
process of individuation okay so the
word individuation there feels confusing
to me probably because I have a meaning
I'm from Texas
so I have a meaningful connection to
more libertarian sensibilities so when I
hear it I map it more in the direction
of that which is stands opposed to
communitarianism some more like
individualism as opposed to
individuation but then I notice what
you're saying that I also have an
awareness of it in the context of child
development right that a child as
teenagers adolescents are individuating
which is that they are discovering who
they are by virtue of themselves for
themselves and becoming capable of being
responsible is that sound like what
you're referring to yeah and maybe it
also links back into the concept of we
can only truly collaborate from a space
of genuine individual sovereignty mm-hmm
and that's the paradox that many people
get hung up on because they want to move
to this space and know we want to
collaborate we want to do this together
but actually you're going to get there
once you've done the inner work to be
able to collaborate from a place of
genuine sovereignty well this is also
very powerful thing in the context of
the false dichotomy they just
articulated there's oftentimes a well
false dichotomy that we I there are
individuals or we are communal it's
either consensus or it's Liberty but
what you're saying and which I agree
with completely is the collaboration
takes place in a space that is that
transcends that dichotomy that it is
precisely to the degree to which we are
most fully individuated that we were
most fully capable of expressing that
which is much meaningful and also most
capable of simultaneously hearing
clearly listening clearly and expressing
clearly because we have become clear
right we've become nothing but that wish
we are and the process of doing that
requires a serious amount of skill
with some of the characteristics that
seem to be showing up in these
individuals are for example courage yes
they have the archetypal virtue of
courage which is sort of notably absent
from ours if someone asks me like why I
even made some music with PS and in the
first place of what I like about him and
the first thing that came to mind was
courage was bravery yeah was someone
standing up for something right whatever
that is in the faces you can imagine
that it like a deep level like in our in
our bones or even in our like
reproductive organs the part of us that
has been all about how the hell do try
and survive has a deep sense of when
there are when there is no courage we're
probably so when when we feel an
absence of courage and then courage
shows up like okay that whatever that is
it needs to happen right and so that's
one one piece and then the other piece
that we also see is like I saw gonna
break this into two one is this notion
of a an unreasonable attraction to the
truth all right so a sense of a
willingness to say to take pain to like
suffer in in defense of what is
perceived to be true right so rather
than being able to capitulate or to
equivocate saying you know I'm just
gonna kind of like come in and say what
I think is true and almost almost
blindly not like calculating when I take
the consequence I think it's a good idea
but for some reason I'm just wired is
one of these people who just can't feel
good about things not being true and
then the other aspect over here is
something about stepping out like a
bigger picture like zooming out and
taking a look at things that are not
right in front of us in trying to say
like wait a minute
something's going on and again like if
you think about this in terms of just
straight evolution you can imagine that
there's a situation where we've been
encamped in a valley for a long time and
it's worked out we've got a good way of
being and but we're noticing for example
that maybe the hunt isn't producing as
well as it was towards a watering hole
seems to be getting drier every couple
of years and most people still are just
kind of like that's not there's not the
thing they just focus on what's going on
but a couple of folks they step back and
like wait a minute what's that mean like
what's happening here and in something
there grow hold on guys we may have to
leave now leaving the valley is
dangerous as going from where you
are and where things working understand
was happening to a new place is a really
bad idea so it's not gonna be
well-received which is why it takes a
certain kind of courage to be willing to
step up and say it but because we've had
to do that a lot to be humans and humans
more than any other animal
we're the only animal that is in fact
designed the ability to get up from a
whole niche like to leave the African
savannah and migrate to the to the
Arctic we're the only animal that has to
have some system that's able to be able
to detect when it's time to do that
alright so then this is the able to step
back and try to figure out okay what is
the basis that we can actually use to
perceive a bigger picture that allow us
to make good choices in an environment
where something is wrong and it's gonna
be very subtle like you can't what name
it very well if it's at the mr. poetic
layer so maybe that's what I think is it
that's what's happening it's showing up
you